{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One district in this city was dubbed “Electric Town” for its booming black market. Six island fortresses were built on the artificial island of Odaiba in this city, which may be reached through Rainbow Bridge. In 1960 in this city’s Hibiya Hall, a nationalist stabbed a socialist politician on live TV; that hall is in this city’s Chiyoda ward. For ten points, name this city where Frank Lloyd Wright’s Imperial Hotel survived the 1923 Great Kanto earthquake.",
      "answer": "Tokyo"
    },
    {
      "question": "This sort of event is the subject of the “Saga of the Seven Suns” in the Pali Canon, in which it is associated with the Maitreya Buddha in a belief that inspired the White Lotus Rebellion. A battle between the forces of Necho II and King Josiah which led to the vassalization of Judah may have inspired one term for this type of event, as possibly did an earlier battle in which Thutmose III defeated the King of Kadesh at the same site. In 2011, Harold Camping planned for, for ten points, what oft-predicted eschatological event described in the Book of Revelation as “Armageddon”?",
      "answer": [
        "End of the World",
        "Armageddon before mentioned",
        "Apocalypse",
        "equivalent descriptions like the Last Days"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One candidate for the Democratic nomination in this election year was a New Jersey senator who had played for the New York Knicks. The South Carolina primary in this year was won by a “compassionate conservative.” This election was the last in which the Green Party nominated Ralph Nader for president; he was accused of causing a spoiler effect in this year. This election saw “hanging chads” cause a long recount in Florida ended by the Supreme Court. For ten points, name this election in which George W. Bush defeated Al Gore.",
      "answer": "Election of 2000"
    },
    {
      "question": "Infighting within this state led to the Battle of Bogesund, in which one side’s leader perished on the frozen Lake Malaren. This state faced a rebellion by Erik Puke, who attempted to fulfill the goals of the earlier Engelbrekt rebellion. The second ruler of this state was Eric of Pomerania; his predecessor defeated Albrecht of Mecklenberg to form this state. A bloodbath caused by the Archbishop of Uppsala, along with the coronation of Gustav I of Sweden, greatly weakened this state, which was founded by Margaret I of Denmark. For ten points, name this medieval union of Norway, Sweden, and Denmark.",
      "answer": "Kalmar Union"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people wrote their own interpretation of the story of Jesus in an epic poem known as the Heliand. 4,500 of these people were beheaded in the Massacre of Verden during their namesake wars, in which Charlemagne attempted to subjugate them and convert them to Christianity. Widukind of Corvey wrote a history of a dynasty named after these people, who established kingdoms such as Sussex and Wessex. For ten points, name these Germanic people who, with the Angles, ruled pre-Norman England.",
      "answer": "Saxons"
    },
    {
      "question": "Prior to this battle, Tychaeus’s cavalry provided reinforcements, but fled during the fighting. A bloody stalemate at this battle was broken by the return of forces under Gaius Laelius and Masinissa. The victor’s plans for this battle were opposed in the Senate by Fabius Maximus. The loser had earlier defeated Gaius Flaminius at Trasimene and Paullus and Varro at Cannae. For ten points, name this victory by Scipio Africanus over Hannibal, the final battle of the Second Punic War.",
      "answer": "Battle of Zama"
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure is the alphabetically-prior namesake of a manifesto that inspired the Pugwash anti-WMD conference; that manifesto is named after this man and Bertrand Russell. David Ben-Gurion tried to make this man the first President of Israel, a post he refused. With Leo Szilard [zee-LAR], this scientist wrote a letter to FDR that inspired the Manhattan Project. For ten points, name this scientist who formulated general and special relativity.",
      "answer": "Albert Einstein"
    },
    {
      "question": "This war was prompted by the death of John Sassamon, and its northern front was called the First Abenaki War. Josiah Winslow led the victorious forces in one of this war’s battles, the Great Swamp Fight. Mary Rowlandson wrote her captivity narrative about this war which was ended by the Treaty of Casco Bay. This war, which destroyed the Narragansett, was named for the son of Massasoit who had sheltered the Pilgrims 50 years earlier. For ten points, name this war in which the New England colonies defeated a namesake Native American leader.",
      "answer": [
        "King Philip’s War or Metacomet’s War",
        "equivalents like “rebellion” for war"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One composer from this country wrote a series of nine suites that fuse Bach-style Baroque harmonies to this nation’s folk music. A drought-stricken ranch in this nation’s sert˜ao is the setting of Glauber Rocha’s film Black God, White Devil, a landmark film in a movement inspired from across the Atlantic by French New Wave called Cinema Novo. Heitor Villa-Lobos is the foremost composer of this country’s classical style. For ten points, name this country whose government hired Lucio Costa and Oscar Niemeyer to plan a new capital city, replacing Rio de Janeiro.",
      "answer": "Brazil"
    },
    {
      "question": "The prices charged by these companies were the subject of Regulation Q. In the 1980s and early 90s, a “crisis” caused over a thousand of one variant of these companies to fail. The Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act repealed one law that mandated separation of two types of these companies; that law, the Glass-Steagall Act, separated their “commercial” and “investment” types. For ten points, name these financial companies that were bailed out in the 2008 financial crisis, modern examples of which include JPMorganChase and Citigroup.",
      "answer": [
        "banks",
        "types of banks like investment banks, commercial banks, etc.",
        "prompt on “financial services” and other generic answers"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A nominally neutral party in this war was led by Teganissorens, who concluded negotiations with the losing side’s commander, Vaudreuil. Aggrieved losers from this war fought Dummer’s War about a decade later. The losing side flauted the treaty ending this war by reconstructing Fort Niagara in 1722. This war’s loser retained Cape Breton, but was forced to cede Saint Kitts as well as Newfoundland and Acadia. Partly fought over the patronage of the Iroquois, this conflict was ended by the Treaty of Utrecht, as it is the North American phase of the Thirty Years’ War. For ten points, name this war, named in America for the final Stuart ruler.",
        "answer": [
          "Queen Anne’s War",
          "Thirty Years’ War until mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Twice besieged and captured by the English in the later 18th Century, this fastness on Cape Breton Island was founded as English Harbor to defend the island during Queen Anne’s War.",
        "answer": "Louisbourg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One politician from this country insisted that Jan B¨ohmermann stand trial for a poem that implied he has sex with goats and watches child pornography. That politician shuttered the main opposition paper in this country, Zaman. This country shot down a Russian Su-24 after it allegedly encroached on its airspace, and it reached an agreement with the EU where it would receive billions in aid in exchange for taking Syrian refugees from Greece. Recep Erdogan is president of, for ten points, what country ruled from Ankara?",
        "answer": "Republic of Turkey"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Turkey has been patrolling the Aegean Sea along with this multinational European organization, which is responsible for helping secure the EU’s borders.",
        "answer": "Frontex"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Seven African-American strikebreakers in this industry were killed along with four of their guards in the 1898 Battle of Virden. The shooting of Baldwin-Felts agents in the Matewan Massacre led to a battle between 3000 strikebreakers and 10,000 workers in this industry at Blair Mountain; those workers were supported by Mother Jones. It’s not oil, but a company owned by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. killed around 20 workers in this industry in Colorado. The fall of natural gas prices has caused numerous bankruptcies in this industry, whose workers often develop black lung. For ten points, name this industry, common in West Virginia, that extracts a solid fossil fuel.",
        "answer": "coal mining"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This aforementioned massacre of Rockefeller’s workers in Colorado took place in April 1914. The state National Guard joined in this massacre, in which two dozen people were killed.",
        "answer": "Ludlow Massacre"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one work in this set, an old woman wields a knife in defense of a woman getting raped. This set was influenced by a set of works by Jacques Callot which depicts scenes from the Thirty Years War. The only identifiable character in this set of works is Agustina of Aragon, who is shown manning cannons in the Siege of Zaragoza. These engravings critique politics following Ferdinand VII’s return to power. For ten points, name this set of 82 prints created by Francisco Goya that depict the miseries of the Peninsular War.",
        "answer": "the Disasters of War series"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other Goya work depicts a mob of angry citizens armed with knives attacking horsemen of the Imperial Guard in Madrid, starting an uprising that was crushed by Joachim Murat.",
        "answer": [
          "2nd of May, 1808",
          "Charge of the Mamluks"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Yorkist pretender Richard de la Pole died during this battle. Another commander killed in this battle, Francois de Lorraine, commanded a group of Landsknechts known as the Black Band. The losing ruler in this battle is misquoted as saying “All is lost save honor” in a letter to his mother Louise of Savoy. Charles de Lannoy commanded the winning side in this battle, where one ruler was forced to give up his country’s claim to Italy in the Treaty of Madrid. For ten points, name this 1525 battle in which Francis I was captured by forces under Charles V, fought just south of Milan.",
        "answer": "Battle of Pavia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "At an earlier Battle of Pavia, Charlemagne defeated what last king of the Lombards?",
        "answer": "Desiderius"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the 16th century, Wang Zi combined his merchant business with this profession, establishing himself on the Goto Islands. Cheung Po Tsai became a member of this profession after being kidnapped by Cheng I, who himself was a member of this profession. Gwanggaeto the Great defeated the Wokou, Japanese members of this profession. After the death of her husband, Ching Shih took control of a large group of these people. In this role, Cai Qian led numerous raids on Taiwan and defeated the Qing [CHING] Navy at Wenzhou. For ten points, name this illicit profession of sea-based thievery.",
        "answer": [
          "pirates",
          "similar answers such as raiders"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Wokou were targeted in this 1419 offensive by the Joseon dynasty, which targeted their base on Tsushima Island.",
        "answer": [
          "Gihae Eastern Expedition",
          "Oei Invasion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man signed his articles as Raro and Eusebius in the Neue Zeitschrift fu¨r Musik. This man wrote a set of works that depicts a hobby-horse and a game of Blind Man’s Bluff and dedicated his Kreislerania to Chopin. The composer of three Romances for violin and piano married this man in 1837, 13 years before their trip to Cologne Cathedral inspired part of his Rhenish Symphony. For ten points, name this composer of Scenes from Childhood who married Clara Wieck [VEEK].",
        "answer": "Robert Schumann"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eusebius makes an appearance alongside Harlequin, Chopin, and Liszt in this other Schumann set of piano works, which are linked by the recurring motif of A-S-C-H.",
        "answer": "Carnaval"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The construction for this project was actually supervised by the designer’s daughter-in-law, Emily, who learned higher mathematics to assist her injured husband. The original engineer for this structure died after contracting tetanus completing a survey for this structure, leaving his son Washington in charge. P.T. Barnum marched a parade of 21 elephants across this structure to reassure the public about its stability. For ten points, name this John Roebling-designed structure spanning the East River in New York.",
        "answer": "Brooklyn Bridge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Cuban poet of Versos Sencillos wrote a poem about “The Bridge of Brooklyn” for its opening.",
        "answer": "Jos´e Marti"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A group made of university students that opposed this man lynched Imperial Minister of War Theodor Franz and was called the Academic Legion. The March Revolution repealed a set of laws issued by this man that were passed after the murder of the writer August von Kotzebue. The incendiary speeches of Lajos Kossuth partially caused this man’s resignation and temporary exile. For ten points, name this reactionary statesman who fled Austria during the Revolutions of 1848, ending this man’s namesake “age” that began with the Congress of Vienna. ANSWER:PrinceKlemensWenzelvonMetternich(acceptClementWenceslasLotharvonMetternich- Winneburg-Beilstein) BONUS: Metternich, the pope, the czar, and this man formed a “holy alliance” against communism, according to Karl Marx. Metternich and this prime minister under Louis-Philippe both supported the breakaway states in the Sonderbund War.",
        "answer": "Franc¸ois Guizot 10 This battle saw Pierre Langlais lead a group of officers nicknamed the “Paratrooper Mafia,” who took charge of a force under the nominal command of Christian de Castries. Strongpoints Eliane and Gabrielle were overrun in this battle in which the defenders included many Foreign Legionnaires. The refusal to give military help, including the use of nuclear bombs, by the Eisenhower administration to the losing side in this battle led to a division at 17 degrees north, as well as the independence of Laos and Cambodia. For ten points, name this battle in which a French force was destroyed by the Vietnamese Communists, ending French control of Indochina. ANSWER: Battle of Dien Bien Phu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This French artillery commander, ashamed for his inability to neutralize camouflaged enemy batteries, committed suicide with a hand grenade at the nadir of the battle.",
        "answer": "Charles Piroth"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "GORE VIDAL",
      "prompt": "In the life and works of Gore Vidal, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "American war that was the subject of his Lincoln: A Novel?",
          "answer": "American Civil War"
        },
        {
          "question": "American politician about whom he wrote a fictional memoir, including a duel with Alexander Hamilton?",
          "answer": "Aaron Burr"
        },
        {
          "question": "religion created by L. Ron Hubbard whose adherents he supported in a letter to Helmut Kohl?",
          "answer": "Scientology"
        },
        {
          "question": "crazy Roman emperor and namesake of a pornographic screenplay by Vidal?",
          "answer": "Caligula"
        },
        {
          "question": "founder of the National Review magazine who debated Vidal on TV in 1968?",
          "answer": "William F. Buckley, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "last Emperor of the Constantinian dynasty who rejected Christianity and was novelized by Vidal?",
          "answer": "Julian the Apostate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Polish director of Rosemary’s Baby whom he defended against statutory rape charges?",
          "answer": "Roman Polanski"
        },
        {
          "question": "1968 novel about a man-turned-woman-turned-man noted for its gender satire?",
          "answer": "Myra Breckenridge"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ROMAN PROVINCES",
      "prompt": "Which Roman province was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "conquered by Julius Caesar in a series of namesake wars in the 50s BC?",
          "answer": "Gaul"
        },
        {
          "question": "annexed by Rome after the Battle of Actium, which was a defeat for its Ptolemaic kingdom?",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "the first province acquired by Rome, a large island conquered after the First Punic War?",
          "answer": "Sicily or Sicilia"
        },
        {
          "question": "where a revolt beginning in 66 AD was brutally suppressed by Vespasian, and later, his son Titus?",
          "answer": "Judaea"
        },
        {
          "question": "annexed after the Antigonid dynasty lost a series of wars which included the Battles of Pydna and Cynoscephelae?",
          "answer": "Macedonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "where a rebellion against Lucius Cornelius Sulla led by Sertorius took place?",
          "answer": "Hispania"
        },
        {
          "question": "the home of pirates that terrorized the Mediterranean before the Lex Gabinia allowed Pompey to crush them?",
          "answer": "Cilicia"
        },
        {
          "question": "annexed after Roman forces destroyed the city of Sarmizegethusa, and whose conquest is depicted on a 115-foot tall pillar?",
          "answer": "Dacia"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "PARAGUAY",
      "prompt": "In the history of Paraguay, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European power that ruled colonial Paraguay and established Jesuit missions there?",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "city established by that power that is Paraguay’s capital?",
          "answer": "Asunci´on"
        },
        {
          "question": "French Emperor whose invasion of that colonial power hastened independence?",
          "answer": [
            "Napoleon Bonaparte",
            "either"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "disastrous 1860s war in which Paraguay fought the combined Brazilian, Argentinian, and Uruguayan forces?",
          "answer": "War of the Triple Alliance"
        },
        {
          "question": "president who launched that war after assuming power from his father?",
          "answer": "Francisco Solano Lopez"
        },
        {
          "question": "ethnicity whose namesake dialect is still an official language of Paraguay?",
          "answer": "Guarani"
        },
        {
          "question": "half-German dictator who ruled for 35 years after a 1954 coup?",
          "answer": "Alfredo Stroessner"
        },
        {
          "question": "party of that dictator that held power until the 2008 victory by the Liberals?",
          "answer": "Colorado party"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this disaster, Senegalese president Abdoulaye Wade offered its victims free land. Missionaries from the New Life Children’s Refuge were accused of kidnapping for attempting to arrange for the adoption of children affected by this crisis. Cholera outbreaks after this disaster were blamed on (20 pts)",
        "Nepalese peacekeepers. Rapper Wyclef Jean tried to run in the presidential election held in the year of this disaster, and (10 pts)",
        "Michel Martelly became president a year later. For ten points, name this natural disaster that destroyed Port-au-Prince in 2010."
      ],
      "answer": "2010 Haitian earthquake"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Foursquare Church was founded in this city by a preacher who later disappeared from a beach off one of this city’s Western neighborhoods. That lady preacher from this city was allegedly kidnapped to Mexico in 1926 and was named Aimee (20 pts)",
        "Semple McPherson. This city saw the founding of the modern Pentecostal movement by William J. Seymour in 1906 as host of the Azusa Street Revival. In the present day, Cardinal Roger Mahoney leads this city’s Catholics, who form the (10 pts)",
        "largest archdiocese in the United States. For ten points, name this West Coast city where preachers often try to convert Hollywood stars."
      ],
      "answer": "Los Angeles"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Hosea Ballou wrote about one quest for these objects which were found at Como Bluff. The Bayanshiree, Djadokhta, and Nemegt formations make up the world’s largest deposits of these objects, which appear in the “Valley of the (20 pts)",
        "Dragons.” Edward Drinker Cope and Othniel Charles Marsh engaged in a notable conflict over these objects. One of these things featuring two creatures fighting to the death was found in the (10 pts)",
        "Gobi Desert, and many have been found in the La Brea Tar Pits. For ten points, name these objects that were the subject of the “Bone Wars,” and which include remnants of creatures such as Triceratops."
      ],
      "answer": "fossils"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man paraphrased Goebbels in claiming “Nothing can be gained by linking ourselves with any organization which is” engaged in “propagating racial hatred.” This man ran the Social Justice, which was targeted by Francis Biddle as a “vermin publication.” This man was supported by Michael (20 pts)",
        "Gallagher, the Bishop of Detroit, who was his superior at the Shrine of the Little Flower. During the election of (10 pts)",
        "1932, this man coined the phrase “The New Deal is Christ’s Deal.” For ten points, name this “Radio Priest” who was forced off the air for anti-government messages in 1939."
      ],
      "answer": "Father Charles Edward Coughlin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Karta of Kabi revolted against a ruler of this state whose doom was spelled by the death of his general, Kanfari Omar. The Tarikh al-Fattash and the Tarikh al-Sudan are the main sources of this state’s history, which includes its victory in the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Anfao and its succession by the Dendi Kingdom after Ahmad al-Mansur defeated it in the Battle of Tondibi. The greatest ruler of this empire had a spiky (10 pts)",
        "pyramid for a tomb, and this empire was founded in Sunni Ali’s revolt out of Gao. For ten points, name this West African empire of Askia the Great that absorbed much of the weakened Mali empire."
      ],
      "answer": "Songhai Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Richard FitzNeal advised this ruler, who printed the “Short Cross” penny. This ruler signed the treaty of Windsor, which placed Rory O’Connor on the throne of Ireland. He ascended to the throne following the signing of the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Wallingford and the end of the Anarchy, and he attempted to curb papal power in the Constitution of (10 pts)",
        "Clarendon. The “Great Revolt” against this man was led by Eleanor of Aquitaine and his son Richard. His knights notably killed the Archbishop of Canterbury, Thomas a Becket. For ten points, name this first Plantagenet king of England."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Descriptive answer acceptable. Before this engagement, the winning commander dismissed enemy envoys by saying that he was not there “to learn its history, but to subdue its rebels.” The temples of the Oracle at Delphi were sacked in order to raise much-needed money for this action, which also resulted in the destruction of a sacred (20 pts)",
        "olive grove. The defending commander, Aristion, partied and ate well while his citizens resorted to cannibalism during this event. The (10 pts)",
        "Long Walls were razed for the final time after, for ten points, what 87 to 86 BC action during the First Mithridatic War, in which a certain Roman general besieged and captured an important Attic city."
      ],
      "answer": "Sulla’s Siege of Athens Siege of Athens”"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This region’ s mythology distinguished between nains and korrigan, who were said to be the spirits of druids who had opposed Christianity. Morvach was the horse of one king in this modern-day region, who could spit fire and gallop across the sea. That king was convinced by Saint (20 pts)",
        "Winwaloe to push his daughter Dahut into the sea after escaping a city she doomed by having an affair with the Devil. That man was King (10 pts)",
        "Gradlon, and this region’s city of Ys [EES] will rise from the sea when Paris is destroyed. For ten points, name this Celtic region in northwestern France with modern capital at Rennes."
      ],
      "answer": "Brittany"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One commander in this battle stationed himself at the easily targeted Sultan Ibrahim building, knowing that the other side wasn’t brave enough to blow it up. Force Z was destroyed prior to this battle. The Alexandra (20 pts)",
        "Hospital massacre took place during this battle, where ANZAC troops were led by Gordon Bennett. After losing the Kranji River, a meeting at Fort Canning convinced one side to surrender, leading to what (10 pts)",
        "Winston Churchill called the “worst disaster” and “largest capitulation” of British soldiers in history. Arthur Percival was the loser of, for ten points, what February 1942 battle for control of a major Allied base off the Malay Peninsula?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Singapore"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote a “Mormon Prophet’s Tragedy” based on his eyewitness account of the mob that killed Joseph Smith. This politician was, with Henry Adams, one of the “Five of Hearts.” Along with John Nicolay, he wrote a ten-volume biography of Abraham Lincoln. After a failed treaty negotiation with Tom´as Herr´an, this man signed treaties with Julian (20 pts)",
        "Pauncefort and Philippe-Jean Bunau-Varilla. This man sent a note to various European powers after the First Sino-Japanese War which formulated the (10 pts)",
        "Open Door Policy. For ten points, name this Secretary of State under William McKinley and Theodore Roosevelt who names the treaty that allowed the building of the Panama Canal."
      ],
      "answer": "John Hay"
    }
  ]
}